Finding Aid for Frank C. Gates Collection 1912-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank C. Gates Collection 1912-2000, 1912-1915
Gates, Frank C. (Frank Caleb), 1887-1955.
3 linear feet
Professor of botany at the University of the Philippines, 1912-1915; later he taught botany and biology at the University of Michigan Biological Station, then at Kansas State College. Unpublished biography written by his son David M. Gates; correspondence written from the Philippines to his parents, family members, and his fiancee; miscellaneous descriptions and drafts of writings pertaining to Philippine vegetation and travels in the Philippines; and photographs.
0142 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. David M. Gates (donor no. 9022 ) and came to the library in October, 2000.
The collection is open for research.
Frank Caleb Gates was born September 12, 1887 in Ravenswood, Illinois. He was a lifelong student and teacher of science, primarily interested in botany, ecology and biology. He developed his interest in science at an early age and was able to expand his knowledge through the use of libraries close to his suburban Chicago home. He completed his undergraduate education at the University of Illinois in 1910, majoring in botany. He continued his graduate and doctoral studies at the University of Michigan, receiving his Ph.D. in Botany in 1912. Gates departed for a faculty position at the University of the Philippines in 1912 where he remained until 1915. During this time Gates documented, through photographs and writings, his observations of the diverse vegetation, geography and climate of that region as well as the culture of its people and the students he taught. He made several excursions to the outlying Filipino countryside that are also well-documented. Gates returned home from the Philippines by way of Japan, China, Hawaii and the Western United States.
Upon his return he married Margaret (Madge) Murray Thompson in Cleveland, Ohio on June 11, 1915. Madge and Frank were neighbors while growing up in Ravenswood, Illinois and the two corresponded frequently throughout Mr. Gates time in the Philippines. Between the years 1915 and 1918 Mr. Gates taught botany and biology at the University of Michigan Biological Station during the summer and at Carthage College in Carthage, Illinois during the regular school term. Mr. Gates moved on to teach for many years at Kansas State College. The Gates adopted two children, David M. and Margaret Elizabeth. Frank Gates died in 1955.
The Frank Caleb Gates papers are divided into four series and are composed primarily of materials relating to his time spent teaching botany at the University of the Philippines and exploring the vegetation of the Philippines Islands (1912-1915). The series include biographical information, correspondence, miscellaneous, and visual material.
Subjects:
Botany--Philippines.; Forests and forestry--Philippines.; Gates, Frank C. (Frank Caleb), 1887-1955.; Philippines--Description and travel.; University of the Philippines--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Botany--Philippines.; Gates, Frank C. (Frank Caleb), 1887-1955.; Philippines--Description and travel.; Plants--Philippines.; Forests--Philippines.
Contributors:
Gates, David Murray, 1921-
Genre/Form:
Postcards.; Lantern slides.; Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Information consists of one bound monograph documenting the life of Frank Caleb Gates written by his son David M. Gates and published in July 2000. The book includes information about the Gates family lineage, the educational background and interests of both Frank and Madge Gates, academic accomplishments of Mr. Gates, family travel, excerpts from published and unpublished writings, photographs, and a bibliography of works written by or about Mr. Gates.
  - Monograph: Frank Caleb Gates Botanist and Ecologist and his Companion Margaret Thompson Gates by David Murray Gates, July 2000 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains both personal and professional materials, with the bulk being personal and written by Mr. Gates to his parents, siblings, and fiancé¥ (Madge) during his time in the Philippine Islands. The letters are arranged in chronological order. The Professional correspondence dates from 1913 to 1915 and consists primarily of correspondence between Mr. Gates and The University of the Philippines. Included among the correspondence series are a limited amount of mementoes and other ephemeral materials collected by Mr. Gates during his travels, including passenger lists, business cards, small diaries, and sketches.
  - Personal 1912-1915
    - August 1912-September 1912 (Box 1)
    - September 1912-December 1912 (Box 1)
    - January 1913-August 1913 (Box 1)
    - September 1913-April 1914 (Box 1)
    - May 1914-May 1915 (Box 1)
  - Professional 1912-1915 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series is arranged chronologically and contains information regarding Mr. Gates' time in the Philippines in the form of notes, drafts, and completed papers primarily on the topic of vegetation on the islands. Titled works include "The Revegetation of Taal Volcano," "Things a Traveler may see in Philippine Forests," and "Philippine Vegetation." This series also contains writings that describe the many expeditions made by Gates during his tenure in the region. Finally, the series contains a March, 1910 issue of The Philippine Journal of Science, which includes annotated maps of routes traveled by Mr. Gates in the Philippines from 1913 to 1915.
  - Notes, drafts, and completed papers describing the vegetation in the Philippine Islands (Box 1)
  - Descriptions and observations from several expeditions on the Philippine Islands (Box 1)
  - Journal: The Philippine Journal of Science, Vol. V March 1910 (Box 1)
- Visual Material
  The Visual Materials series consists of four subseries (photograph albums, negatives, lantern slides, and postcards) containing visual documentation of Mr. Gates' stay in the Philippines as well as his lengthy journey home through Japan, China, the Hawaiian Islands and the Western United States. The seven albums created by Mr. Gates (and his contemporaries at the University of the Philippines) capture the images of his journey, primarily the vegetation found on the Philippine Islands. He has assigned a number to each image. These numbers correspond to the negatives also contained in this series. The negatives are contained in 105 envelopes and arranged numerically in the box. It is important to note that in this box, there are additional negatives whose original photograph is not contained in the albums. These negatives cover the years immediately following Mr. Gates return from the Philippines. This series also contains a small box of lantern slides produced from select negatives from the Philippines trip, as well as slides used by Mr. Gates in academic course instruction (at the University of Michigan Biological Station among other institutions). The final material in this series consists of a box of postcards collected throughout Mr. Gates' stay in the Philippines and on his voyage home through Japan and China.
  - Photograph albums 1912-1915 (Philippine Islands)
    Photograph albums, 1912-1915, of images taken while in the Philippines and on the trip home via Japan, China, the Hawaiian Islands, and the western United States. The photographs are illustrative of Philippine vegetation, local customs, and general travel views of people and places. There are also photographic negatives of the images in the albums, and lantern slides and postcards with images of the Philippines, Japan, and China.
    - October 1912-July 1913 (593-1200) (Box 1)
    - July 1913-November 1913 (1201-2200) (Box 1)
    - November 1913-May 1914 (2201-2800) (Box 1)
    - May 1914-November 1914 (2801-3400) (Box 1)
    - November 1914-March 1915 (3401-4038) (Box 2)
    - 1913-May 1915 China, Japan, Hawaii, Ocean (4039-4462) (Box 2)
    - 1913-1915 Philippine Islands (Box 2)
    - Index to Photograph Albums (Box 2)
  - Lantern slides
    - Views of the Philippine Islands and Japan circa 1915 (Box 2)
    - Educational slides (Box 2)
  - Postcards
    - Views of the Philippine Islands, Japan, and China, 500 postcards approximate (Box 2)
  - Photographic negatives
    - nos. 608-5435, 105 envelopes (Box 3)